IL Cafe we have you covered
the end of September sees our s observed
were
worth day it's a good time to focus on
your health on the lifestyle choices
that you're making and indeed on some of
the other aspects of cardiovascular
Wellness welcome to aisle Cafe my name
is ashidil and today we've decided to
catch up with two experts to help us
understand a very important topic and
that topic is CPR
now you must be wondering what is CPR
right well you've seen it and um I have
to say unfortunately in this country a
lot of us have only been exposed to CPR
on screen on Cinema or some you know
television serial that sort of a thing
where we've seen a person deliver cardio
pulmonary resuscitation to a patient in
need or someone in need but the thing is
what is fortunate is that there is
information available on what CPR is
it's only about connecting the right
experts with the right information to
the Right audience so we're going to
talk a little bit about CPR today on our
World Heart Day related podcast it comes
ahead of the day itself and who are the
who are the guests who are going to be
joining me over here well our guest
speaker today is none other than Dr
ravneet Wilko he's an anesthesiologist
with a diploma in critical care uh more
than 10 years of experience in ICU as a
specialty and critical candy heads in
fact critical care for surana hospital
in shimbur in Bombay so that's a little
bit about Dr Wilko and there's also our
guest from The icso Lombard World who's
joining us Dr Sharma I should say Dr
Akash Sharma he's a as you guessed it a
doctor himself by education he's also an
ex-entrepreneur and someone who has a
deep interest in experience in
healthcare Tech so that is going to be a
big part of our chat on on the show
today he currently leads outpatient
Health Products wellness and the IL take
care application strategy for the
organization thank you so much to the
two of you for joining us on IL Cafe
today welcome to the show how are you
good well I'm good good to know that the
people in charge of other people's
Health are good you know it's always a
good thing to hear that but my first
question for you is uh you know it's for
you Dr Wilko we've heard so much about
CPR right that phrase or the
abbreviation is now not a uh you know
uncommon one for all of us why is it
important for us on this special podcast
to be aware of what CPR is all about
well that's an absolutely good question
you know first things CPR or
cardiopulmonary resuscitation you know
it's a life-saving technique you know it
can be used when somebody is breathing
or heartbeat stops suddenly so it's a
combination of chest compressions and
rescue threats which can be given at a
specific time and you know it can
restore the vital organs with the blood
circulation and it can increase the
chances of somebody surviving a cardiac
arrest so CPR basically educating people
about it it generates awareness and
people can be First Responders in such
kind of situation so this Bridges the
Gap you know till you know the pros
arrive at the scene basically Cardiac
Arrest can happen anywhere at any time
to anybody so you know nobody is out of
risk in today's world so basically
learning is very easy and accessible to
all you know being ready to use CPR can
make a massive difference in a crisis
situation and mainly you know in you
know it makes Common People a hero at
that moment so yes it is very important
to save somebody Life by giving CPR
Whenever there is a event or whenever
there is a cardiac arrest you know when
you say anyone can actually learn uh CPR
do you really mean that or do I have to
have some sort of a like medical
background to be able to administer CPR
to someone in need
so CPR has two components it has a basic
life support and an advanced cardiac
like support so when you talk about a
basic like support anyone anyone with no
medical background at all can run it at
any point of time it's just a single day
Source a few hours into it and you are
an expert now I absolutely agree with Dr
Wilko on this and I believe uh the
golden uh is what we refer to and I
believe in a country like in India where
the health the or the health systems
doesn't know emergency and support
doesn't come immediately
uh accessibility is a challenge yeah
more so in a tier two and three cities
it's good to have somebody around us who
can administer this or save life or
ourselves being knowledgeable uh to do
this to the people I believe through
this relative some people will get that
benefit look over to that right yeah so
I'm going to come back to you Dr Wilko
uh tell us what are the various steps
involved in CPR to somebody what's uh
what do you do when you find yourself in
a situation like this
no no absolutely you know CPR is just a
series of steps so make sure that the
person who's in Cardiac Arrest is lying
flat on a hot surface you know so place
the peel of your palms on the lower
middle part of the chest bone you know
and start with your interlocked fingers
so you know then you can start
compressing the chest the compression
should be at least two inches deep and
100 to 120 in a minute and we just have
to make it so that after every 30
compressions we have to give a rescue
breath to rescue breaths and when we are
giving the rescue breath we should be
sure that there is a chest rise so that
we know that the breath is going inside
now the app is just repeated till the
paramedics or the help arrives
Dr Sharma anything that you would like
to add what Dr Wilko said this is more
effort to buy three C's or five series
of CPR itself right so that means check
for breath and Consciousness and then uh
seek help or check for him third one is
uh uh cover the nose and the nose and
then the third word last one will be the
agriculture compressions right so that
normally is how the CPR normally in
simple sense to understand what are the
few steps and how you need to go about
it is kind of a thought or the educated
yeah yeah so there you go our experts
have given us an understanding of the
steps involved in administering uh CPR
or cardiopulmonary resuscitation to
someone in need hopefully that never
that moment never comes in your life and
everybody is safe and healthy again
wishes on the occasion of World Heart
Day that comes up later in September but
to move into the next question right uh
Dr Wilco we still notice a lot of people
who are a little bit apprehensive when
it comes to you know getting into the
groove of action uh doing the right
thing and saying okay I know CPR and I
can either maybe you know help him
somewhere they hold back a little bit
what do you think this is the case so
with some of us well that's an excellent
question you know uh there are several
reasons first of all I would like to say
that it's a fear of making mistake or
causing any harm it's like when you're
giving CPR or chest competitions there
is always a possibility of breaking a
rib but you know breaking a rib is still
better than not doing it at all you know
and uh secondly you know maybe many
aren't aware that how crucial CPR is and
how easy it is to learn so thirdly some
people you know hesitate to step in
during emergencies you know often due to
uh feeling powerless or anxious so these
things are abolished when you learn CPR
you know once you know it you can jump
into the situation and be the hero that
the person needs and where does one be
earn you know I forgot to ask you this I
ask you for steps very smartly I did
that but then I forgot to ask where does
one learn this right but how does one
learn to be your first responder are
there courses that are available in this
particular area there are there are
courses courses around like I said BLS
basic life support so there are few
institutes which teaches such courses
and it's a single day course so you can
just uh check it online and find the
nearest one to yourself and get enrolled
yeah please make a note all of our
viewers on the particular podcast
2023 yeah there aren't too many months
really left of it soon we're going to be
making resolutions for the next year but
we are not there yet we still have a few
months and like uh Dr Wilco said it it
just takes about a day of training and
then you can go back for a refresher
course as is required uh let me come to
the next question that I have for you
with respect to anxiety you've addressed
it right
um motivate people to learn CPR and also
overcome these hesitations so education
and awareness are the key you know we
need to spread the word about the
importance of CPR and how
straightforward it is to pick it up you
know offering CPR trainings in schools
workplaces communities it can make a
huge difference around now plus legal
protections like a Good Samaritan act
you know whenever person you know helps
somebody who's in Cardiac Arrest should
not worry about the legal implications
of it so if people are protected in
right sense I think they're they will
you know jump into the situation and try
to help somebody absolutely and be the
hero of the day Dr Sharma what about you
yes yeah so I would say that the main
aspectives awareness and education and I
feel that we don't emphasize that enough
from our probably there shouldn't be
something that should be taught at
school level or High School level at
least uh it's a good skill it's uh
something that's very useful because
event can happen uh with anyone with any
age group right it's important to
understand how to do it it's important
to when to do it and also more important
to understand how to do it correctly so
all this can be covered at the in a
right setting and I think we should
start at the school level at least for
college level to build more
Consciousness around the CPR as well
absolutely I can't agree with you more
Right In fact when you look at the
broader Financial awareness space as
well a lot of experts that I've spoken
to on typical Money Matters related
things also say you know why don't we
start this sort of thing early in life
and same thing with life-saving skills
maybe you know as you've rightly pointed
out needs to be part of the curriculum
and it's not that difficult I would
imagine to implement one of these as a
subject you know schools and colleges
but let's come to something else that
you seem to be very very passionate
about technology and Healthcare coming
together in one person and that person
is Dr Sharma so tell us about you know
we have something very cool over here
and ICS University I'll take care app
can you tell us about this One-Stop
wellness and insurance solution if I may
call it that so uh the I'll take care
application it comes from a single of
Pisces we are the number one private
insurance company of India we have built
this platform
that it should give users uh enabling
tool in which they can assess their
health and considering cardiac health is
one of the key area and one of the major
risk for us as a nation right where the
lifestyle decisions are the highest the
space can too basically plays a very
good uh role in that so uh the feature
of the face scan is such that if you
have the application you can just scan
yourself for 30 seconds just kind of
phase and give you some primary risk
indicators about your cardiac one would
be your blood pressure it will give you
something about your oxygen saturation
but also gives you something about your
cardiac variance right right it's an
indicator will also tell you that it is
an indicator that helps you understand
that how receptive or how sensitive is
your cardiac function because I mean the
stress that you have now the stress
could be an active the stress or the
passive stress and it can lead to all
sorts of treatment and unfortunately but
in many cases it can can make an
individual recipient or the likelihood
secret of CPR itself the subject matter
that we have here so I we feel that
there's something that we bought out
it's a it's a serious so uh certified
feature it is and uh something that
people should have in their pocket and
should use it off
I completely agree with you and this is
the day and age of Technology coming or
you know inserting value into our lives
and spaces that we didn't believe could
be revolutionized by technology at all
and Dr Wilko I'm sure you've seen this
right amongst your patients who are
bipping out of course there's always
Google Dr Google is always consulted
before Dr Wilco that must be a thing
that really annoys you but uh we have to
live with this sort of reality but I'm
sure you know you're also uh sort of
bladdened by the way people are adopting
technology to stay fit whether it's a
Fitbit that you're wearing or any
wearable device uh CGM you know now
nowadays I see a lot of people who don't
have diabetes and yet want to figure out
what their blood sugar picture is all
about so they implant themselves as one
of those you know devices tell us what
you think of this coming together of
something like you know like an I'll
take care an app uh with Technologies
like face scan built into it and you
know people being able to focus on their
own health well certainly the FaceTime
feature is a standard aspect of the I'll
take care app you know it lets the user
check their key Health vitals in a
single phase can like Dr Sharma also
said in a 30 seconds and you get all
your vitals in your hand so it's a quick
and easy way to monitor your health on
the go so I guess in today's
technological advancement uh Health
should also be one of the priorities and
you know this health field should also
advance in a similar way so this does
help everybody around to get healthy and
with the monitoring that they need I
would say absolutely I can't agree more
with you you know things like face
scanner are truly of value instead of
watching Netflix watch the face scanners
available on the on the I'll take care
no comment because I'm constantly
watching internet Netflix myself so
please go ahead and enjoy but you know
exactly what I mean uh Dr Sharma to come
back to you right some of the other
benefits and features if you can
highlight about the ilt care app that
would be great for our viewers so apart
from the cardiac function monitoring
that FaceCam offers we also have certain
other features that help in
self-assessment for example we have a
HRA which helps your users that it's a
very effective way of user to engage
with the application and tell about what
the things they're doing right and wrong
and get a score out of it and also apart
from that there is a doctor assistance
that is their nutritionist so it's
basically whole ecosystem centered
around people living a healthier life
with all the coaches experts and uh
assessment tools that can be enabled
through a digital feature while such as
tracking your steps if you want to track
it to the application also a mental
coach and counselor as we have on the
application so whole host of that thing
created and curated for our some of our
policyholders and uh even if you're not
a policy holder you can still go on an
application and uh use a tele Rock
feature speak to other doctors and seek
a consultation so that's something we
will get open and even the physical is
open for everyone so I mean the
application is there for people to
access and use and will be happy if
people take benefit of that and
something comes to mind on an earlier IL
Cafe episode I remember one of our
leaders in the organization has spoken
of how this is more about the health of
the individual this is not really about
the insurance aspect the product aspect
of it really you know comes much later
so I love the way the focus is really on
the individual and them taking their own
health and lifestyle into their hands
and then thinking about insurance is
just one of the things that happened in
the course of that mindset that we are
trying to develop like focus on yourself
absolutely right absolutely so the
intention of what I'll take care is that
moving uh just uh with our our
relationship with the policy who's not
moving not just as a facilitator of uh
risk coverage but moving to as a
custodian of careful and I'll take care
basically becomes that Hub that offers
all those enablements and engages us
with our policy order in that light I'm
going to wrap up we've spoken quite a
bit about the I'll take care app you've
spoken about FaceCam we've had Dr
wilko's views on Tech and Healthcare as
well uh with one last message from the
both of you since your experts and Dr
Wilko you're indeed someone from
critical care as a as an area of
specialization is it a message that
you'd like to leave all of our viewers
on the occasional World Earth Day we do
know that cardiovascular illnesses are
you know one of the number one killers
in this country along with diabetes
um
something on CPR would be good to get
some words of wisdom to wrap up from you
well at the end I would just like to say
okay in today's world uh you have to
take care of your heart you cannot take
it for granted and age is not a factor
as of now you know I've seen people with
the age of 20 also talking dead so one
should you know learn and no CPR so that
they can offer it you can offer it to
somebody you don't know but you know if
there is a conditional situation in your
own family and you are unable to help it
out you know that guilt stays for a very
long time so take care of yourself give
your health a priority use the hand Taps
you know I'll take care of it and see
all good things and to learn CPR
with either a professional training or
at least take a course or see how it's
done on the internet if you don't have
time to go anywhere but you know learn
this important tool and let it be there
with you at every point of time anything
Dr Sharma would like to add so thank you
so I think I'll second what you just
said and I believe that uh CPR the what
we're focusing on right now more and
more people should make themselves
familiar with it uh understand that the
help is at that particular time the help
is only going to be coming from the
person next to you and that person at
that time if you did fail to take
initiative to make them aware or educate
yourself for it then at the end of the
day you should share the partly of a
blame if you missed out
right so it's important for all of us to
definitely be aware about CPR yeah and
thank you to the two of you for joining
us on a special podcast on the special
episode in fact around World art day and
I want to say something to you which on
behalf of all of our viewers I would
imagine you know most people in the
healthcare space never get told they get
asked for advice you know first person
to call if you have a doctor in the
family Dr Wilko and Dr Sharma must be
very aware on speed dial you know I have
a cold today can you tell me what I
should be taking no matter what your
specializations have seen that happen to
doctors in the family but please do take
care of your health as well and thank
you so much for the great work that both
of you do in your respective fields for
the health and well-being of each one of
us thank you for joining us today thank
you thank you for having us
yeah thank you